Ask a bunch of main framers what makes their platform so powerful, and there's a good chance
a good number of them will tell you it's Sysplex.
Simply put, Sysplex is a way of making multiple systems work together as a team, and this
can be L-Pars on one physical box, or it can be spread out across many.
Before we get into exactly how it does this, we first have to define a couple of basic
concepts.
First, there's STP, the server-time protocol.
Systems need to be an exact agreement about time, like exact agreement.
And that kind of makes sense if you've got multiple systems writing to the same file,
milliseconds apart, and you're trying to figure out which one got to that piece of
data first.
Having your watch is synchronized is kind of important.
Then there's GRS, the global resource serialization.
This allows for multiple systems to access the same resources concurrently, serializing
where necessary to ensure exclusive access.
Without GRS, you have quite a mess.
That's a handy rhyme.
You should remember that, in case you're tested on it later.
XCF, the cross coupling facility.
This manages communication between applications and Sysplex.
This also lets you be logged into one system, and issue commands on behalf of another
system in that Sysplex.
This right here is what lets the Sysplex communicate as a whole.
Next up, the coupling links.
These connect L-Pars to processors.
Without these accessing memory on different physical systems, would have to run through
one of those L-Pars.
And these allow direct memory access communications between Sysplex memory and the memory
of an attached system.
Finally, there's the CDS, the couple data set.
So imagine you've got a bunch of people working on the same job.
Let's just say they're tallying up the numbers of different colored candies they're
getting from various bags of candies.
Bags of candies.
Anyway, they're all working together to get one final result, which means they're all working
on the same set of data.
Now in order to coordinate this operation, so someone doesn't accidentally overwrite someone
else's work, there needs to be an additional file that keeps track of who is currently
working on a resource.
So everyone knows how to wait their turn.
That's the CDS.
These parts are super important when you're talking about Sysplex, because without them,
you've just got another distributed environment.
Those memory links, the tightly coupled resources, and of course being an absolute lock
step on time is the only way this will all work.
We talked a little bit earlier about WLM, the workload manager.
It's the component that makes sure that high priority work gets run quickly and that
all of our targets are met.
WLM makes quite a bit of use of Sysplex to help balance things out.
So if that discussion earlier about performance tuning on the mainframe was interesting
to you, Sysplex is something you want to pay close attention to.
Sysplex is, at its core, a bunch of ZOS operating systems working together.
They're able to cooperatively use hardware, software, and components to achieve a high availability
workload processing environment.
This gets us back to the whole physical logical discussion, and when you have systems
in a Sysplex, when you're talking about how they're going to handle the work, you essentially
have one entity that is running the work.
It's the Sysplex.
Even though you know that you've got multiple physical mainframes and within those multiple
logical L-Pars, you'll often hear people just refer to it all collectively as the Sysplex
or just the Plex.
Let's talk about those Sysplex configurations.
There's three main ways you can configure a Sysplex.
Now, bit of a riddle.
If you've got a Sysplex with only one L-Par in it, is it really a Sysplex?
The answer is yes, and it's called a monoplex.
Now, you'll often see a monoplex in testing and staging situations.
But beyond that, it doesn't really buy you any additional performance or functionality.
Then there's this concept of a base Sysplex.
In this configuration, every system has a connection to every other system.
And they all know about each other and they all agree to do work together.
It's almost like they started a little band.
The most common form of a Sysplex, though, is the parallel Sysplex.
In this configuration, instead of needing every system connected to every other system,
we have this concept of a coupling facility.
This is a special type of L-Par that you bring up.
And typically, you have backups of it on other mainframes, too.
In a parallel Sysplex, the coupling facility handles all the complexities and
overhead of those systems working together.
So you can have up to 32 ZOS images and up to 32 physical mainframes.
That would mean one L-Par on each mainframe hooked into a 32-way Sysplex.
Now, most systems aren't scaled out that way.
But if you need to, you could do it.
Now, a word about availability.
You might hear people say that a mainframe environment hasn't gone down in decades.
But how is that possible, and that's the running on 20-year-old hardware and software?
Well, one of the neat things about being an Sysplex is you can do what's called a rolling
IPL.
An IPL is just booting up an operating system, and a parallel Sysplex doesn't require
all the systems in it to be up in order to function, just enough to keep it running.
So if I've got 16 L-Pars in my Sysplex, we're just saying, I can bring down four of them,
help date the operating systems on them, and then bring them back up and put them into
the plex.
L-Pars got upgraded, and the plex stayed up.
I can even do this with physical systems as long as some of the members are running elsewhere
in another mainframe.
So let's go back to those 16 L-Pars.
Say they're spread out across four mainframes, just as an example.
And we want to upgrade one of those mainframes to a shiny brand new one.
We bring down the four L-Pars on that system that we want to replace, physically swap
it out with a new one, cable it up, configure it the way we want to, power it back on,
IPL, or boot up those four systems on the new hardware, very them back into the plex,
and we're good to go.
The plex never went down.
That is some pretty amazing stuff, and you can see why so many people would tell you it's
their favorite feature.
Although it's hard to pick just one, isn't it?